It is the Sengoku Era
A time of war
Several hundred years ago
That's pretty weak.
ちょろいな
Like child's play.
まるで子供遊びだ
You must be crazy, trying to follow the way of the sword with skills like that.
よくもまあそんな腕で剣の道を志そうとしたものよ
I'm sorry to say this kid, but you've got no talent for the sword at all.
こう言っちゃ何だが小僧よ
お前には剣の才能ってもんがまったくねえ
You've got no muscle, no form, and most importantly, you lack the resolve to kill.
筋は悪い形もなってねえ
それに何より人を斬ろうっていう気概が感じられねえよ
If you want to get better with a sword, the first thing you have to do is kill.
剣の腕を上げてえんならまず人を斬らねえと話になんねえ
剣士ってのは３００人斬ってそれでようやく半人前だ
A swordsman is still only halfway to maturity after killing 300 people.
もっともお前は葉っぱさえ斬れねえみてえだがな
Right now, you wouldn't even be able to cut a leaf...
I took the time out of my busy schedule to take a trip to the capital's suburbs for this?
忙しい中京くんだりまで足を延ばしてみたけどよ
チェッ　俺も焼きが回ったみてえだ
Maybe I'm losing it too...
道のりが見えずらしくもなく焦っちまったってことか
I guess I panicked when I lost sight of my path.
Path?
道のり
From perfection to completion.
完成から完了へのな
完成から完了
Perfection to completion?
What do you mean?
どういう意味だ
I mean exactly what I said.
そのまんまの意味に決まってんだろうが
まあ見たところ完了どころか完成にも程遠い
Well, seeing as you're nowhere near perfection, let alone completion,
it's probably just rambling from your amateur point of view.
未熟なお前には関係のない領域の話かもしれんがな
俺の剣が未熟なことくらい分かってるさ
I know my skills aren't up to par.
だからこうして　修行にいそしんでるんじゃないか
That's why I'm training like this.
I admire your dedication, at least.
その心掛けは褒められる
しかし小僧よ
But kid, if you keep dawdling around like that, the war's going to end.
もたもたしてっと戦国が終わっちまうぜ
Huh?
山ん中に引きこもってちゃ世間のざまなんざ知らねえだろうけどな
Though, if you're cooped up on a mountain like this, you probably don't know anything about the world.
I don't care.
関係ねえ
Oh?
俺は自分の腕を磨くことしか興味はない
The only thing that interests me is honing my own skills.
剣の道ってのを究めたいだけだ
I aim to master the way of the sword.
The country may be at war or at peace, but the path ahead of me will not change.
時代が戦国だろうが太平だろうが
俺の歩む道筋は 何も変わらない
What's so funny?
何がおかしい
いや心掛けだけはホントに褒められるもんだと思ってよ
I was just thinking that your dedication really is all I can admire.
それに　世の中に興味がねえってところも気に入った
And I find it interesting how you don't care about the world.
I originally thought this was a pointless trip, but it looks like you might just barely pass.
無駄足だったと思ったがまあぎりぎり合格ってとこかな
What?
I also have no interest in the world.
俺も実際　世の中なんか興味はねえ
俺が相手取ってんのは何たって歴史ってやつだからな
I guess what you could say I'm fighting is history itself.
If you look at the world and everything in it from the perspective of history, all you see is the surface of it.
世の中やら世界なんてもんは歴史全体から見たら
表面のほんの上澄みみてえなもんにしかすぎねえ
What's with you?
何なんだあんた　誇大妄想狂か何かか
Are you a megalomaniac or something?
あながち間違っちゃいねえな
That might not be entirely wrong.
まあ大半の人間にとって俺はそういう立場なんだろう
Well, most people probably see me that way.
だからこそ俺は結果で勝負しなけりゃならねえんだけどな
That's why I have to fight for results.
しかしそれでももう少しってところでうまくいかねえ
Even then, as close as I get, it still isn't enough.
やっぱ素材の問題なのかねえ
Maybe it really is a problem with the raw materials.
That aspect of it is really just luck.
こればっかりはどうしようもねえ
何の話をしている
What are you talking about?
Oh, I guess I didn't tell you.
ああまだ言ってなかったな
俺は刀かじだ
I'm a swordsmith.
And what does a swordsmith want with me?
その刀かじが何の用だ
小僧　てめえの涙ぐましい努力が花実を咲かすよう取り計らってやろう
Kid, I'm going to take all that passionate effort of yours and make it blossom into flowers.
Of course, whether or not the roots also grow will be entirely up to you.
もっともしっかりとした根っこになれるかどうかはお前しだいだがな
Yasuri Kazune.
鑢一根
This happened several hundred years ago,
それは数百年も昔の話
この世が乱世と呼ばれ この国が戦国と呼ばれていたころのお話
when the country was at war, a time now called the Sengoku period.
Now it is but an ancient tale.
今は昔の物語
後の虚刀流開祖 鑢一根と
It was the beginning of the story of the man who would later found Kyotouryuu, Yasuri Kazune,
この時点ですでに伝説の刀かじ 四季崎記紀との
and the swordsmith of legend, Shikizaki Kiki.
これが　なれ初めでございました
Dokutou
Mekki
Gild,
the Poison
「絶刀·鉋」
Zettou Kanna.
「斬刀·鈍」
Zantou Namakura.
「千刀·つるぎ」
Sentou Tsurugi.
「薄刀·針」
Hakutou Hari.
「賊刀·鎧」
Zokutou Yoroi.
「双刀·鎚」
Soutou Kanazuchi.
「悪刀·鐚」
Akutou Bita.
「微刀·釵」
Bitou Kanzashi.
「王刀·鋸」
Outou Nokogiri.
「誠刀·銓」
Seitou Hakari.
And with that, we've managed to collect ten of Shikizaki Kiki's Perfected Deviant Blades.
四季崎の完成形変体刀もどうにかこうにか１０本集まったわけだ
１０カ月もかかっちまったけどな
Though it took us ten whole months...
いい　やむしろ上出来と思っていいのだ
No, it's amazing that we did it so fast.
そうなのか
Really?
旧将軍のみならず かつて誰も成し得なかったことだ
It's a feat that Shogun Kyuu and many others failed at.
それをこの短期間のうちに　われらだけで１０本も集めたのだぞ
Consider that in such a short time we've already assembled ten of them.
むろん　わたしの頭脳を持ってすれば可能であると
Of course, I was sure it was possible to begin with because of my superior intellect.
初めから確信していたことではあるがな
時折己の才覚が恐ろしくなるよ
Sometimes I even scare myself with the extent of my skills.
己の才覚って　奇策で刀を奪ったのって
Skills?
Did your strategies ever actually win us the swords?
ちぇりお
Cheerio!
実際は半ば力ずくで奪ってきたような
Most of them were taken by force.
それも奇策のうちだ
That's also a part of my strategies!
そなたという刀をどう扱うかが　わたしの腕の見せどころだったのだ
My role was figuring out how to use you, the sword, most effectively.
And are you any good at that?
うまく扱えてるのか
むしろ上出来だと言ったであろう
I already said that what we've done is amazing!
そうか　それならいいんだ
Is it?
That's fine then.
As long as you remain my sword, I'm sure everything will go well.
そなたがわたしの刀であってくれるかぎり
万事うまく運ぶであろうよ
Oh!
Look, a tea stalk is standing.
見ろ　茶柱が立っておるぞ
That's a good omen.
幸先が良い
残りの旅の成功を祝福しているようではないか
It's like a blessing for the remainder of our journey.
ただの茶柱だろ
It's just a tea stalk.
縁起物というのはだな
You only have to look at good omens whenever things are going well.
都合の良いときだけあやかっておけばよいのだ
そういうものなのか
Is that how it works?
そういうものだ
That's how it works.
残りの旅か
The remainder of our journey, huh?
That's right, there isn't much left, is there.
そうだ　残りわずかな旅だ
I'll let you play with my hair tonight.
今度は髪を触らせてやる
There isn't much to play with.
触るほどないじゃないか
何をー
What?
So that's who you really are, Strategian Togame.
それがあんたの正体
奇策士とがめ
わたしはさぁ あんたのことが本当に嫌いで
You know, I truly hate you, from the bottom of my heart.
心の底から大っ嫌いで
正直　たとえあんたが何者であろうと
Regardless of if you were important or not,
たとえあんたが何もたくらんでいなくとも
or weren't scheming anything in the shadows,
どのみちつぶしてあげるつもりでいたんだけどさ
I was planning to smash you anyway.
あんたとは敵対していたつもりだったし
I intended to go to war with you,
I even felt a strange bond with you in that regard.
そこに変な絆さえ感じていたし
これからもそのつもりだったけどさ
Well, I still intend to, but that's precisely why,
でもだからこそ
こんな形であんたと決着をつけたくはなかったわね
I didn't want to settle things with you like this.
とても残念だわ奇策士
What a pity, Strategian.
I truly can't stand your carelessness.
あんたのうかつさがひどく憎々しい
Oushuu
Dewa
通さず
Impassable.
ここで張っていれば現れると思っていたよ真庭鳳凰
I figured you'd appear here if I waited, Maniwa Houou.
そして真庭人鳥だったか
And Maniwa Pengin too.
Allow me to introduce myself first.
聞かれる前に名乗らせてもらうぞ
わたしは左右田右衛門左衛門
I am Souda Emonzaemon,
お前たちを殺す者だ
the man who will kill you.
In case you're wondering, I killed Maniwa Oshidori.
ああ 真庭鴛鴦ならわたしが殺したはあ
真庭海亀もわたしが殺した
As well as Maniwa Umigame.
ほう 海亀たちをなぁ
So you're the one responsible...
状況がのみ込めたか真庭鳳凰
Do you understand your situation, Maniwa Houou?
真庭忍軍十二頭領も残すところ　お前たち２人というわけだ
Of the 12 Maniwa Corps heads, you are the only two remaining.
ほ　鳳凰さま
H-Houou-sama!
It would be really pathetic if you truly thought you could scare us with such talk.
そんな言葉でわれを脅しているつもりだとすれば　心底片腹痛い
Ninja live and die, that is all.
忍びは生きて死ぬだけだ
変わらないなお前は
You haven't changed.
お前は何も変わらない　鳳凰よ
Nothing about you has changed at all, Houou.
I haven't changed?
われが変わらないだと
You make it sound as though you knew me from long ago.
まるでわれのことを昔から知っているかのような物言いではないか
Surely you must know by now.
お前だって本当は分かっているはずだろう
いや 伊豆で接触したときにもう分かっていたはずなのだ
No, I'm sure you already knew when we met in Izu.
聞き捨てならないな
I can't let that one slide.
何より聞き捨てならないのは
However, what's even more inexcusable is a name like "Souda Emonzaemon".
左右田右衛門左衛門などというふざけた名のことだ
If you really are who I think you are, then you should announce your name straight up, with pride.
お主がもし本当にわれの思っているとおりの者だとすれば
堂々とそう名乗ればよかろう
あいにくこれが今のわたしの本名だ
Unfortunately, that is my real name now.
わたしはお前とは違う
I am different from you.
You certainly have changed.
確かにお前は変わったよ
Get back.
下がっていろ この場所ではお主の忍法は使えまい
You can't use your ninpou in a place like this.
あっはい
O-Okay.
P-Please be careful, Houou-sama.
き 気を付けてください鳳凰さま
T-This is the man who k-killed Umigame-sama and Oshidori-sama.
う 海亀さまと鴛鴦さまをこ殺したというのなら
He's no pushover.
あの男の実力は
I know that.
分かっておる
His strength is probably on par with mine.
あの男の実力はおおよそわれと同じくらいといったところか
Undeniable.
禁じ得ず
That's quite funny.
失笑を禁じ得ないな
わたしとお前の実力が同じくらい
Our skills are on par?
Of course they are.
そんなことは当然だろう
海亀にも鴛鴦にも 相生拳法は通じなかったので
Aioi Kenpo didn't work on Umigame and Oshidori, so pardon me if I skip that step.
悪いが手順を省かせてもらう
そもそもわたしは剣士ではない
I'm not even a swordsman to begin with.
That's true.
それはそうだ 持っていろ
Hold this.
得物はなしだ それでいいな
No specialized weapons.
Agreed?
えっと 右衛門左衛門だったかな
So, Emonzaemon, was it?
Right, Emonzaemon.
そうだ 右衛門左衛門だ
鍛え上げた自らの肉体と技術のみでの勝負
A contest of pure skill and discipline of the body.
I like the sound of that!
それも悪くあるまい
He's trading blows equally with Houou-sama.
鳳凰さまとあそこまで渡り合えるなんて
But if Houou-sama can get within range...
けど 鳳凰さまの射程に入れば
Danzaien!
断罪円を
鳳凰さま 忍法·断罪円をお使いください
Houou-sama, use Ninpou: Danzaien!
ほう お前はあの技を断罪円などと呼んでいるのか
Oh? So you call that move "Danzaien"?
真庭人鳥よ
Maniwa Pengin.
お前が言うところの忍法·断罪円は
The Ninpou that you call Danzaien was called Namagoroshi by the Aioi Clan.
相生忍軍においては忍法·生殺しと呼んでいた
Ninpou
Namagoroshi
N-Namagoroshi?
な 生殺し
And now I call it Shinobazuhou Ikasazukorosazu.
TL Note: No sneaking, no sparing, no killing.
そして今わたしはその技のことを 不忍法·不生不殺と呼んでいる
Shinobazuhou Ikasazukorosazu
N-No way, he's...
まっまさかあいつは
皮肉なものだな 鳳凰よ
It's quite ironic, Houou.
お前は優れた忍びだ
You are an excellent ninja.
真庭忍軍の頭領がどれだけ目減りしたところで
Even were you to be the sole surviving Maniwa Corps head,
お前一人残っていれば
それだけで真庭忍軍はじゅうぶん脅威となるほどに
that would be more than enough to make the Maniwa Corps a threat.
しかしだからといってわたしは お前に負ける気がまるでしない
Nonetheless, I do not feel that I can lose to you.
なぜなら お前はわたしだからだ
Because you are me.
I died once.
わたしは一度死んだ
Not physically, but mentally died.
肉体はともかく精神的に死んだ
しかしその死を否定してくださったのが 今のわたしのあるじだ
But one person denied me that death.
My current master.
ならばこそあのあるじからの命を執行するために
And now I put all my soul into following her orders.
わたしは全霊を尽くす
So it's true, your master is that princess.
やはり お主のあるじはあのお姫さまか
You just realized that?
今さらだろ
右衛門左衛門よ お前がわれだと言うならば
Well Emonzaemon, if you claim that you are me, then I am also you.
われもまたお前だ
As we continue fighting, I may not defeat you, but I will not lose to you either.
このまま続けたところで
勝てないまでもお前に負けることはないだろう
かもしれない
Possibly.
彼らは 旧知の間柄
They were once friends with each other...
忍法を奪った間柄
They learned Ninpou from each other...
殺し殺された間柄
They dealt and saw death beside each other...
H-Houou-sama!
ほ 鳳凰さま これを これをお使いください
H-Here!
Please use this!
That was a mistake
Wh-What?
鳳凰さま
Houou-sama!
H-Houou-sama?
鳳凰さま
Dewa
おい 生きてるのか
Hey,
think he's alive?
刀傷だな
It's a sword wound.
こいつは
This is...
H-Help.
た 助けて
Please help.
助けてください
It doesn't matter what happens to me,
ぼ 僕のことなんてどうでもいいから 鳳凰さまを助けてください
but please save Houou-sama.
これわななんじゃないのか
Could this be a trap?
予定変更だ この辺りですぐに宿を取るぞ
Change of plans.
We're going to find an inn nearby.
Daikokuya
Inn
Houou-sama took the sword and headed for Iga.
鳳凰さまは 刀を持って伊賀に向かわれました
Why would he wound one of his allies?
何で 仲間のお前が殺されかけたんだ
Houou-sama has gone insane.
鳳凰さまは 乱心されました
「毒刀·鍍」か
Dokutou Mekki.
P-Please!
ど どうか
I understand, so just get some rest!
話は分かった 寝ていろ
ほ 鳳凰さまを
H-Houou-sama...
ど どうか 鳳凰さまを
Please save Houou-sama!
Several days later
ほ 鳳凰さま
Houou-sama...
Assuming what this boy says is true,
その小僧が言ったことが本当だとすれば
we can't afford to stick around much longer.
いつまでも足を止めているわけにはいかぬな
俺はまだ半信半疑だけどな
I still don't trust him though.
いかにも嘘くさいし
He's not telling the whole truth,
またぞろ何かのわなって線もあるんじゃねえのか
and there might still be a trap somewhere in this.
Yeah.
まあ 相手が相手だ
Well, knowing the Maniwa Corps, that wouldn't be surprising.
考えられなくもないか
And is this guy really a Maniwani to begin with?
そもそも 本当にこいつまにわになのか
I can guarantee that.
それは保証する
真庭忍軍十二頭領が一人真庭魚組 真庭人鳥だ
He is one of the 12 Maniwa Corps heads, Maniwa Pengin of the fish squad.
十二頭領の中でも 真庭鳳凰に次いで恐れられていた忍者だよ
He's the ninja that was feared the second most amongst the 12 heads, after Maniwa Houou.
This guy, huh?
こいつがねえ
I heard he wields a Ninpou that may someday surpass even Maniwa Houou.
真庭鳳凰をも凌駕しかねない忍法の使い手だと聞いておったが
Really?
そうなのか
回復が遅いのが気になるな
It's strange that he's recovering so slowly.
これが 「毒刀·鍍」の特性なのか
I suppose that's Dokutou Mekki's focus.
His speech has also gotten strange.
話し方もつかえつかえだしな
He's always talked that way.
それはもともとだ
Really?
そうなのか
Pengin's Ninpou is one beyond that which even his own body can stand.
それこそ
人鳥の忍法は自身の手にさえ余るものらしくてな
Apparently that's the reason he developed such an un-ninja-like personality.
結果
ああいう気弱で忍びらしからぬ性格に仕上がってしまったそうだぞ
You know a lot about him.
詳しいな
蝙蝠のやつから聞いた話だ
I heard about it from Koumori.
まあ ずっとこうしているわけにもいかぬであろう
Well, we can't just stay here forever.
出発だ
Let's go.
I won't disagree that this may be a trap, but our objective from the start has been collecting swords.
わなである可能性も否めぬが
もとよりわたしたちの目的は刀集めだ
真庭鳳凰が「毒刀·鍍」を所有しておるというのならば
If Maniwa Houou has gotten a hold of Dokutou Mekki then we have to go after him anyway.
それを収集していかぬ手はなかろうよ
ややこしい取引を仕掛けられるよりはよっぽど安心できる展開だ
And this is far simpler than having to come up with tricky negotiations or whatnot.
That's too tight, idiot!
バ バカ者 締め過ぎだ
Ah, sorry.
ごめん ごめん
So what do we do with him?
それよりあいつはどうするんだ
Just leave him here?
放っておくのか
Well, given how he looks, I'm sure the innkeeper won't just throw him out onto the street.
あのとおりのお子さまだ
はたごの者もむやみに放り出したりはせぬであろう
So that's your reasoning?
そういう考えか
いや そういうことじゃなくってさ
I didn't mean that though.
憎き真庭忍軍の一人を
He belongs to the Maniwa Corps, our enemy.
何つーのか ここでやっつけとかなくていいのか
Shouldn't we just deal with him now?
You mean kill him here?
それは 殺せという意味か
確かに真庭忍軍は憎いがな
It's true they're our enemy.
But I don't enjoy killing with no reason.
しかし 意味のない殺しをしてもしかたあるまい
わたしはそこまで暴的な人間ではない
I'm not one who enjoys bloodshed.
We could use it as a negotiating point.
恩を売るのも一つの手だ
真庭忍軍の者が恩を感じぬとしても
And even if the Maniwa Corps don't recognize that, we can call upon it as a debt.
貸しはつくれよう
なに その貸しは
And at some point after our sword collection journey is over we can claim that debt.
私達の刀集めの旅が終わった後にでも返してもらえばよい
それだけの利用価値がこの忍びにはある
There are several reasons why he might be useful alive.
Ah!
All right, let's head out.
では 向かうとしよう
新·真庭の里とやらへ
Our target is the New Maniwa village.
So they're headed for the New Maniwa village?
そう 新·真庭の里に向かったのなら今ごろは東海道かしらね
They're probably around Tokaido right now then.
Well, go finish off the last of your duties, at least.
こうなったらせめて 最後の役割だけは全うしてよね
でも 手ごわいわよ
It'll be hard, though.
虚刀流がどれほどのものか知らないけれど
I don't know how strong Kyotouryuu is,
わたしのご先祖さまはとてもとても手ごわいわよ
but my ancestor is very, very strong.
He has powers that weren't passed down even to me.
何せ彼ときたら
わたしまでには受け継がれなかった能力を持っているのだから
だから せめて有終の美を飾りなさい
So at least die beautifully for me.
If we stop by Owari, I'll be obligated to visit the castle.
尾張に寄れば わたしは立場上登城せざるを得ぬからな
And that would mean having to face that princess.
それに またぞろお姫さまと対面せねばならぬことになろうよ
はあ 面倒なもんなんだな
Sounds troublesome.
ああ 面倒だ
Yes, troublesome.
こうして１人 今は２人か
So right now, working alone, or rather, with you, is far easier and more constructive.
それで行動している方がいくらも気楽だし 建設的だ
So, this New Maniwa village?
しかしなぁ 新·真庭の里ってのは
I'd never have guessed it'd be in Iga.
まさか よりにもよって伊賀だったとはな
That's the place where the Shogunate originally kept its secret service headquarters.
もともと幕府が抱えていた隠密集団が根城にしていた地域だ
Right under our noses.
盲点であったな
Come to think of it, this is my first time in Kansai, oddly enough.
そういえば 関西圏は初めてだな
意外といえば意外だけど
I guess you could say it's surprising, but all we did was stay in the capital at the beginning for a bit, right?
最初のころ京にちょっと滞在した程度か
Well...
We started on the island you grew up on, Fushou.
まず そなたの故郷である不承島
で 因幡 出雲 巌流島 薩摩 蝦夷 土佐
Then Inaba, Izumo, Ganryuu Island, Satsuma, Ezo, Tosa,
Edo, Dewa, Mutsu,
江戸 出羽 陸奥
そして伊賀
and now Iga.
道のりも考慮すれば
If you include the in-between traveling, we've pretty much toured the entirety of Japan.
軽く日本を一周しておる感じかな
北陸地方が少し弱いといえば弱いか
Though I guess we only touched on the Hokuriku region.
刀集めの旅が終わったら
When this sword collection journey is over, it might be fun visiting there again together.
あらためてその辺りを旅してみるのも面白いかもしれぬな
そうして全国地図を描いて売り出すのだ
And then we can draw a map of the whole country and sell it.
You already know I'm good at drawing maps, right?
わたしが地図を描くのが得意なのは知っておろう
いい加減な測量に基づくものは多く出回っておるが
There are plenty of maps based on sketchy measurements out there,
but this would be the first ever precisely drawn atlas of the whole country.
精巧な全国地図といえば
この国が始まって以来 まだ誰も作ったことがない
I'm sure it'd sell for a lot.
だからかなり高く売れよう
いや そうだ １２本目の刀もまだ残ってるじゃないか
Well wait, we still need to find the 12th sword first.
I already have a pretty good guess of where Entou Jyuu is.
「炎刀·銃」の在り処はおおよそ推測がついておる
所有者もな
As well as its owner.
If you think about it, Princess Hitei has been pretty proactive about this sword collection.
考えてみれば
否定姫はこの刀集めに対して 最初から積極的であった
１本くらい自分の手元に置いておきたいと考えたとしても
It wouldn't be strange if she were to keep one for herself nearby.
不思議ではあるまい
Given that Emonzaemon has been going around killing the Maniwani,
右衛門左衛門がまにわにを殺しているのならば
it's logical to assume that she currently holds Entou.
炎刀は現在 あの女の所にあると考えるのが妥当だ
I see.
そうかしかしどうしてお姫さまはそのことを俺たちに黙ってるんだ
But why wouldn't she tell us that?
そなたの頭は 単純な上に平和だな
Things always seem rather peaceful in your head, as well as simple.
１本でも完成形変体刀を持っているかぎりにおいて
If she keeps at least one of the Perfected Deviant Blades in reserve,
わたしたちと取引が可能になるであろう
she'll still have a hand in negotiating with us.
うまく振る舞えば 手柄を全て横取りすることさえ可能になる
If she plays her hand right, it's possible she might even steal credit for the entire thing.
It's exactly the same plan that the Maniwa Corps had.
真庭忍軍が取ろうとした作戦とまったく同じだ
Well, knowing her, I'm sure her intentions aren't so simple as just stealing the spotlight.
まあ あのお姫さまのたくらみがただの手柄の横取りとも思えぬ
わたしをつぶすための策略を練っておるのかもしれぬな
Perhaps she's planning some strategy to destroy me.
She's already interfered a bunch of times over the course our journey.
これまでも色々仕掛けられたじゃねえか
Those little trip-ups were nothing but playing around for her.
あんなの あのお姫さまの仕掛けとしては遊びのたぐいだ
あの女が本腰を入れたら あんなものでは済まない
When that woman makes her real move, it won't be pretty.
Of course, the same goes for me.
もっとも それはこちらも同じだがな
Either ways, if our final opponent is Princess Hitei, then it'll be business as usual for me.
いずれにしても 最後の相手が否定姫だとなれば
これはわたしにとってもいつものことだ
いつものこと
As usual?
そう だから刀集めの旅も おおよそ終わりだと言ったのだ
Right.
That's why I said our sword collection journey is almost over.
Hey, Shichika...
なあ 七花
Are you going to stay by my side even after this journey's over?
そなた この旅が終わった後も
わたしのそばにいてくれるつもりはあるか
Unlike Princess Hitei, I've never had a confidant or right hand man for any long period of time.
わたしは 否定姫と違って
腹心や懐刀といえる者を 長期間にわたって持ったことがない
ただただ 邪魔なだけだからな
They'd only have gotten in my way.
That's why I've trusted no one, and lived my life destroying any personal relations I'd made.
だから 信頼関係はおろか
人間関係さえも短期的に崩すように生きてきた
否定姫を何度も蹴落とそうとしたのも
The countless times I've tried to beat Princess Hitei also has that kind of purpose, on top of self-defense.
保身以上にそういった意味合いもあったのだ
But I don't want to do the same to you.
しかし そなたに対してはそういうことをしたくない
Originally I only intended to keep you as a partner for the duration of the sword collection journey,
最初はな そなたとは刀集めの旅の間だけの相棒のつもりであったが
but with the Maniwa Corps and Sabi Hakuhei gone, I need your power.
真庭忍軍も錆白兵もおらぬ今 わたしにはそなたの武力が必要だ
Our sword collection is almost done, but my own fight isn't over yet.
刀集めの旅はもうすぐ終わりだが
わたしの戦いはまだ終わりではない
In fact, the road after we finish collecting them all might be even tougher.
場合によっては 刀を収集し終えたその後の方が大変かもしれぬ
だ だから そなたの武力がわたしには必要だ
That's why I need your power.
I need the peace I feel when I'm with you!
そなたといるときの安らぎがわたしには必要なのだ
故に 鑢七花 そなたにはわたしの腹心になってもらいたい
So, Yasuri Shichika...
I want you to be my trusted partner!
But...
でも 俺は鑢六枝の息子だぜ
I'm Yasuri Mutsue's son, you know?
Yeah.
あんたの父親を殺した鑢六枝の息子だ
The son of the Yasuri Mutsue who killed your father.
So what?
それがどうした
別に そなたが殺したわけではあるまい
It's not like you killed him.
When Yasuri Mutsue died, any grudge I had against Kyotouryuu died with him.
鑢六枝が死んでいるというその段階で
すでに虚刀流に対するわたしの復讐は済んでおる
In fact, when you consider that he died by your hand, it's all the more reason!
ましてや
その六枝をそなたの手で殺しておるというのならなおさらだ
Regardless of that, I have no reason to hold any grudge against you!
そうでなくとも そなたを恨む理由はわたしにはない
Am I wrong?
違うか
Well, it's not like I have anywhere to return to, anyway.
どうせ俺には帰る場所もないしな
And Nee-chan's dead too.
姉ちゃんも死んじまったし
If you want to continue keeping me with you, I don't need any other reason.
もしあんたが俺を雇い続けてくれるなら それ以上のことはない
それに 俺はあんたにほれてるんだからな
Besides...
I fell for you.
Really?
そうか よし では行くぞ
All right, let's go then!
Okay!
And so they made quick progress towards Iga.
そして 一路２人は伊賀へと向かいました
However, they had no way of knowing that historically, the end of any journey is the end of everything.
しかし２人はこれまでの歴史上全ての旅人がそうであったように
旅の終わりは やはり全ての終わりであることを
まるで知る由もなかったのでございます
H-Houou-sama!
ほ 鳳凰さま 鳳凰さま
Houou-sama!
鳳凰さま
Houou-sama?
Houou?
鳳凰 違うな
You're mistaken.
俺は 四季崎記紀だ
I am Shikizaki Kiki!
奇策士
That Strategian...
That witch left me alone.
鬼女があんなふうに日和るなんて
Not only did she not kill me,
命を取らないまでも
she didn't even bother breaking my legs or anything.
脚くらい折っていくこともできたはずなのに
In the past she'd never be this lenient.
昔の奇策士ならそうしたはずだ
That woman is rotten to the core.
あの女はよ　腹ん中腐ってんだよ
立ち振る舞いから言動から全てが計算ずくだ
Everything, from the way she acts to the things she says, are cold and calculated.
To her, we're nothing but numbers in her formula.
俺らのことなんざ ほんの数式としか思ってねえ
It's not even funny.
ホント 笑えねえよ
Has that Kyotouryuu changed the Strategian?
あの虚刀流が奇策士を変えたというのか
真庭の里に戻らないと
I have to return to the Maniwa village!
行かさず
Unallowable.
I don't see the Strategian or Kyotouryuu anywhere.
奇策士と虚刀流の姿が見えぬな
入れ違いになったか
It seems I missed them.
Well, whatever.
まあ いい　走ればすぐに追い付ける
I'll catch up to them soon enough if I run.
B-Because of you, Houou-sama has—
お前のせいで 鳳凰さまは
Because of me?
わたしのせい　確かにそのとおりだが
You're correct, but I don't think you can accuse me of anything.
それで お前になじられる覚えはないな
We are enemies, after all.
わたしとお前は敵同士だろ
真庭人鳥よ
Maniwa Pengin.
お前は子供だから
You are a child, so some may believe it appropriate to grant you lenience and let you go.
情けをかけて見逃すべきだという考えもあるが
But I see things differently.
しかし わたしの意見は違う
If I leave a ninja with such an unpredictable temperament alive,
お前のような感情が不安定な忍者を生かしておいては
後々まで 禍根を残し
you will undoubtedly be troublesome sometime in the future.
姫さまのためにならない
I must act for the sake of the Princess.
真庭鳳凰がああいうことになった以上
With Maniwa Houou in that state, the only choice I have now is to destroy the Maniwa Corps entirely.
真庭忍軍には滅びてもらうしかないだろう
Well, this is my judgment to make, in the end.
まあ あくまで わたしの独断だが
I did not expect you to act as you did, Maniwa Pengin.
お前の行動は予想外だったぞ 真庭人鳥
だからこそ お前に対してわたしは出し惜しみをしない
And that is why I will allow no hesitation in facing you.
I will use Entou Jyuu from the start.
いきなりこいつを 「炎刀·銃」を使わせてもらう
E-Entou?
え 炎刀
I missed?
外れた
No, he made me miss.
いや 外されたか
It's useless.
無駄だよ
As long as that Entou shoots projectiles, it's useless against me.
その炎刀　それが飛び道具であるかぎりは 僕には通用しない
それが 僕の忍法 運命崩しだ
That's my ninpou, Unmei Kuzushi!
TL Note: Fate ruination
Unmei Kuzushi
なるほど
I see.
斬りつけられても死なずにこうして生きている
You remain living as you are, even when attacked.
幸運 いや 論理を無視するほどに強運ということか
You have great luck, no...
Your luck is strong enough to defy even logic.
確かに 十二頭領の一人に選ばれるだけのことはある
I understand now why you were chosen as one of the 12 Maniwa Corps heads.
This is the decisive moment.
正念場だ
この状況を打破すれば
If I can come out the winner of this fight, I'll be able to obtain one of Shikizaki Kiki's swords.
僕は四季崎の刀を手に入れることができる
どんな強力な物であれ
Regardless of how strong they are, it's a fact that projectile weapons won't work on me.
飛び道具が僕に通じないのは確かだよ
弾丸の方から 僕をよけていく
The bullets themselves dodge me.
飛び道具と限定したな
So it's limited to projectiles?
その忍法　万能ではないというわけか
In other words, that ninpou doesn't make you invincible?
僕の忍法は それだけじゃない
That's not my only ninpou!
Oh?
They call me "Pengin the Multiplier".
僕の通り名は増殖の人鳥というんだ
Do you know why?
それがどうしてか分かるかい
No idea.
さあな　分身の術でも使うのか
Can you use cloning techniques or something?
Close, but not quite!
当たらずといえども遠からずだ
I was wondering what it'd be.
何だと思えば
この武器は柔球という
This weapon is called Juukyuu.
最初はゆっくりに見えるけど
It seems to move slowly to start...
What?
I see.
なるほど
運命崩しとの合わせ技というわけか
It's a move that complements your Unmei Kuzushi.
Juukyuu will continue to accelerate.
柔球は加速し続ける いつまでもかわせるものじゃない
You won't be able to dodge it forever!
So it would seem.
そうらしい
It's useless.
無駄だよ
Maniwa Pengin.
真庭人鳥　お前がどれだけ今の時代に愛されていようと
Are you confident that the world will continue to love you hundreds of years into the future, as it does now?
数百年後の世界でも愛され続けている自信はあるか
歴史的な運命はそう簡単に崩せるようなものではないということだ
I'm saying that the fate of history is not something that can be so easily broken!
Looks like three hit.
当たったのは３発か
Well, fair enough.
まあ そんなところだろう
ど どうして
H-How?
Of course, I got the idea from your Juukyuu technique.
もちろん発想のもとはお前の柔球術だ
I figured that if I ricocheted bullets like your Juukyuu, some might hit you.
あの柔球のように反射させた弾丸ならば
お前に当たるかもしれないと考えた
Ricochet? In this room?
は 反射 こんな部屋で
Unerroneous.
外れず　鉄は鉄に反射する
Iron will deflect iron.
お前が受けている寵愛が永遠ならば
If the love fate had for you were to last forever, the bullets would have probably rebounded towards me instead.
はね返った弾丸はわたしに向かっただろうが
I'm afraid that your luck did not last hundreds of years into the future after all.
残念ながらお前の運も 数百年後までは通じなかったようだ
Wh-What are you saying?
な 何を言ってるんだ
Unnecessary.
いらず
There is no need for you to understand.
お前が理解する必要はない
案ずるな　すぐにとどめを刺してやる
Do not worry.
I will finish you now.
If you have any last words, I will hear them now.
最後に何か言いたいことがあるなら聞いてやろう
I-I don't want to die!
死にたくない　僕は戦いたくなかったんだ
I didn't want this fight!
そんな情けないことを言って死ぬのは歴史上お前が初めてだ
You must surely be the first one in history to die with such pathetic words!
Several days later
Iga
新·真庭の里か
The New Maniwa village...
This is terrible.
これはひどいな
Why did he do this?
なぜ こんなことを
Your sister isn't the only one who can demolish a village.
里を全滅させるのは
そなたの姉の専売特許というわけでもなかろうよ
I knew the Maniwa Corps were in fairly desperate straits.
しかし 真庭忍軍は相当困窮していたとは知っていたが
女子供まで皆殺しか
But to think even the women and children were slaughtered.
This is beyond insane.
乱心どころの話ではないな
どうした
What's wrong?
いたぞ
There he is!
That was close.
危ないところだった
For a moment, I thought that sword was Dokutou Mekki.
危うくあの刀が「毒刀·鍍」なのかと勘違いするところだったぜ
A Perfected Deviant Blade forged by Shikizaki Kiki would never look so normal.
四季崎記紀の作った完成形変体刀が
あんな まともな形をしているわけがないもんな
とがめ どうやらあいつ どっかに毒刀を隠しているみたいだぜ
Togame, this guy must be hiding Dokutou somewhere.
うむ そのようだな
Indeed, it would appear so.
人鳥が言っておった情報とあの黒刀は一致するが
It must just be a coincidence that the black sword he has matches the description Pengin gave us.
それは おそらく偶然であろう
四季崎記紀の刀があんなまともな形をしておるわけがないのだからな
There's no way one of Shikizaki Kiki's swords could look so plain.
I figured it'd be some kind of liquid sword, but what do you think?
まあ 液状の刀だと予想するがどうだろう
I see, not bad reasoning.
なるほど 悪くない線だ
I can hear you, you know.
聞こえてるぞ お前ら
ずいぶんと好き勝手言ってくれるじゃねえか
Having fun running off your mouths?
俺の愛らしい刀どものことをよ
And at my beloved swords, no less.
It seems that no matter the era, young folks will always be rude.
どんなに時代は変わっても若い連中の言うことは変わんねえな
若い　おい貴様
"Young"?
Hey, you!
貴様 本当に真庭鳳凰なのか
Are you really Maniwa Houou?
いいや 違うな
No, I'm not.
俺は 四季崎記紀だ
I am Shikizaki Kiki.
Are you screwing with us?!
ふざけてるのか
It's hard to believe what he says, but Houou was never one to joke around.
にわかには信じられぬ話だが
しかし鳳凰は冗談を言う人間ではなかった
Seems that way.
そうらしいな こいつの記憶の中にあるぜ
His memories tell me likewise.
You must be the "Strategian".
お前奇策士ってんだろ
You have quite a colorful method of fighting.
なかなか 味のある戦い方してんじゃねえか
好きだぜ 俺は そういうのも
I like that type of thing.
お初にお目にかかり光栄の至り
"It is my humble pleasure to make your acquaintance",
とでも言えばいいかね 四季崎記紀殿
I suppose should be my line, right?
Shikizaki Kiki-dono.
Right.
しかしこいつの記憶にあるお前と
Though, the memory of you that this guy has is a bit a different from the one I see now.
今のお前の姿は違うな
You cut your hair?
髪を切ったのか
What a waste.
もったいねえ
それじゃまるでお子さまだ
You look like a kid now.
It's true that I haven't met Houou since my hair was cut.
確かに 髪を切ってからは鳳凰と会っていないからな
あいつ 本当に四季崎なのか　とがめ
Is this guy really Shikizaki, Togame?
体は鳳凰のままらしいがな
It looks like the body is still Houou though.
Well basically, after being moved from place to place, I've finally managed to get a convenient body.
まあ 巡り巡って俺四季崎記紀は
好都合な体を手に入れることができたってわけだ
Is that Dokutou Mekki's focus?
それが 「毒刀·鍍」の特性なのか
A preserved record of your memories.
記憶の保存の転写
I want to say it should be impossible, but I'm too shocked.
あり得ないとは言わんがあきれるな
Well, it's something like a dose of deadly poison.
まあ 猛毒投与ってところさ
"Houou" signifies an immortal bird.
鳳凰はそもそも 不死の鳥を意味する
その肉体をしてすでに死んでおるはずの魂が蘇るとは
It is the height of irony that a long-dead swordsmith has been resurrected in such a body.
何とも皮肉なものだな
TL Note: Life Binding
This guy's ninpou is called "Inochi Musubi".
こいつは今まで忍法命結びとやらで
He steals parts from various people and uses those to lengthen his lifespan.
散々 人の体の部分を取り集めてきて乗っ取ってきてんだからよ
肉体や技術だけじゃない
And not just the physical parts or the techniques either.
He also takes their personalities.
人格までもかりそめだ
He borrows them temporarily.
かりそめの借りものだ
自分という存在を メッキで塗り固めてきたようなもんだ
Kind of like gilding over his own existence and letting it harden.
So isn't it natural that he would get taken over by someone like me in the end?
だから 最終的に こうやって
俺みたいな者に乗っ取られるのもやむなしってところなんじゃねえか
自業自得か
He brought it upon himself.
ところで 四季崎殿
By the way, Shikizaki-dono.
わたしたちをこの地へ招いたのはいったいどういう腹積もりからか
What exactly were you planning to accomplish by calling us here?
Calling?
呼び寄せた
Stop playing games.
とぼけるのはよせ　真庭人鳥を伝言役にしたであろう
You used Maniwa Pengin as a messenger!
そうなのか
He did?
そうだっけかなあ
Ah, yeah, I guess.
Why did you leave Pengin on that road?
なぜ あの道へ人鳥を逃がした
That was part of my predictions.
予測できてたんだよ
Predictions?
予測
Not predictions, but rather, foresight.
予測 ってか 予知だな
実は俺 予知能力者なんだよ
I'm actually a soothsayer.
い 今 何と言った
Wh-What did you just say?
You didn't hear me?
聞こえなかったのか
A soothsayer. I'm a soothsayer.
予知能力者だよ 予知能力者
I simply foresaw that you'd pass through that road.
お前らがいずれ あの道を通ることを軽く予知しただけさ
So you're like a prophet?
占い師 ということか
Right.
There was a time I lived on that.
そんなことをして生きていたころもあったな
そもそも四季崎の家は代々 戦術士の家系だ
Actually, the Shikizaki family has been one of soothsayers for generations.
予知能力といわれても
I find it difficult to believe you when you call yourself something as vague as a soothsayer.
漠然としてにわかには信じ難いな
当てずっぽうじゃないのか
Maybe he just got lucky?
That would be far easier for me to accept.
そうだとした方が よっぽど得心がいく
Oh really?
そうかい そうかい
しかしよ 奇策士
But think about it, Strategian.
If what I say is true, then doesn't it explain the Deviant Blades I created?
そう考えりゃ俺の作った変体刀に説明がつくってもんじゃあねえのか
Or rather, if you don't believe me, it's impossible to explain them.
そう考えねえと説明がつかないって言った方が正確かもしれねえが
H-Hey, what's he talking about?
な なあ どういうことだよ
完成形変体刀に限らぬ
Not just the Perfected Deviant Blades.
変体刀１０００本 全てが
He created all thousand Deviant Blades by reverse importing production techniques he learned by looking into the future!
予知した未来から逆輸入した技術で作られていたのだ
The future?!
未来 逆輸入
Reverse importing?
だから現代のわたしたちには
That's why to us, in this age, it seems like they have special focuses that surpass the laws of physics!
物理を超越した特性を有しているように見える
Precisely. You live up to your Strategian title.
ご明察 さすがは奇策士殿だ
まあ驚きこそすれ 意外というほどではないな
Well, as surprising as it is, I suppose it's not entirely unexpected.
No wait, that's definitely unexpected!
いや待て 意外だろ
そうとでも考えんと説明つかん
There's no other way to explain it.
物理の限界など そうそう超えられるものではないということだ
The limits of physics aren't something that can be broken so simply.
Exactly.
そういうこと
At their core, the Deviant Blades are just regular Japanese swords, except they also exploit physics and psychology.
変体刀はあくまで物理学と心理学にのっとった
ただの日本刀だよ
So why did you create swords like those?
そなたはどうしてそのような刀を作った
Huh?
You told us you came from a household of fortune tellers.
もともとそなたは占い師の家だと言ったではないか
So I did.
言ったな
占い師という職業には
Fortune tellers are supposed to at best give hints about the future,
せいぜい未来を暗示する程度しか許されておらぬはずだ
but you had a hand in it by deliberately scattering the Deviant Blades throughout the country.
なのにそなたは 変体刀を全国へばらまいた
As it happens, my goal has always been to alter history.
あいにく俺の目的は そもそも歴史の改変にあったからな
改変
Alter?
改ざん と言った方が分かりやすいか
Or maybe it'd be easier to understand if I said "falsify"?
That has always been the goal of my family.
それが俺たち一族の本当の目的だったんだ
何のために
For what purpose?
本来の歴史にあった幕府の転覆
In order to overthrow the Shogunate of the original history.
Though personally, I don't really care.
まっ 俺にとっちゃどうだっていいことだけどな
本来の歴史だと
The Shogunate of the original history?
The Itezora family and the Maniwa Corps were both theoretical possibilities that never actually existed in the original history.
凍空一族にせよ真庭忍軍にせよ
本来の歴史には存在しなかったはずの可能性だ
And probably, you as well,
たぶん お前だってそうだぜ 奇策士とがめ
Strategian Togame.
T-Togame?
とっ とがめ
My father gave his life for the sake of restoring the history you altered back to its original state!
わたしの父はな
そなたが改ざんしたという この歴史をあるべき姿にするため
命を落としたよ
Oh?
へえー 四季崎の家系でもないくせに気付いたやつがいたのか
Someone outside of the Shikizaki family realized it?
Hey!
じゃあ 虚刀流も本来は存在しなかったってことかよ
Are you trying to say that Kyotouryuu should never have existed?
Oh, Kyotouryuu?
ああ 虚刀流か お前は違うよ
You're different.
お前は俺がつくった刀じゃねえか
You're a sword that I created, after all.
You met Higaki, right?
彼我木のやつに会ったんだろ
He must have told you then.
そのときに聞いているはずだがな
Kyotouryuu is the final Deviant Blade that I created,
虚刀流ってのは俺がつくった最後の変体刀
the Completed Deviant Blade, Kyotou Yasuri.
完了形変体刀 「虚刀·鑢」だってな
The founder, Yasuri Kazune, didn't reach a complete state,
初代の鑢一根じゃまだ完了とはいえなかったが
やつの張った根は決して無駄じゃなかった
but the foundations he laid weren't for naught.
After all, Yasuri Shichika,
鑢七花 お前のような刀を生み出すことに見事成功したんだからな
he succeeded in producing the sword that you are now.
Y-You knew the founder?
しょっ 初代のことを知ってるのか
I didn't just know him, he was my closest friend.
知ってるも何も親友だよ
Though, he was kind of an idiot who had no interest in history or anything besides swords.
歴史になんか何の興味もないただの剣術バカだったけどな
だがあいつのおかげで
But thanks to him, the forging of my Deviant Blades is now completed.
俺の変体刀作りはこうして完了した
おいおい そうにらむなよ虚刀流
Come on, don't glare at me like that, Kyotouryuu.
あいつにはいくら感謝してもしたりねえし
I can't thank him enough.
Besides, I'm kind of like your father too.
だいたい 俺はお前の父親みたいなもんなんだぜ
俺の父親は親父だけだ
The only father I have is my Dad!
What a heartless guy.
薄情なやつだな
だがそれでいい
That's fine, though.
誰しも自分の出自なんざ気にする必要はねえのさ
No one really needs to care about their origins.
自分は自分でしかねえんだからよ
You live only your own life, after all.
That doesn't apply to people who are already dead.
死んだ人間が抜かしよるわ
１年近くそなたが未来の技術で作ったという
For about a year, I traveled through every nook and cranny of this country,
following your Perfected Deviant Blades that you apparently made with techniques from the future,
完成形変体刀を追って 日本国中を津々浦々まで旅をし
たいていのことは経験したつもりだったが
and figured I had experienced the majority of what awaited me.
最後にその作り手に会うことになったという
But though I never imagined I'd meet their creator at the end,
when I think about it, it's a very sequential, even ordinary way for things to have transpired.
この展開は考えてみればひどく順当で
平凡とさえ言える
I've met a holy man, and could probably even meet ghosts.
仙人にだって会ったのだ
幽霊にだって会えるだろう
つまらぬ展開だ
This plot is turning into a bore,
故にお上に提出する報告書には
so I probably won't even mention you when I hand in my report to my superiors.
そなたのことは記さずに済ませるだろうな
What a cruel thing to say.
ひどい話だ
Isn't that also falsifying history in its own way?
それはそれで歴史の改ざんだぜ
This is a stance that a genius swordsman will come up with in about 150 years.
これはな
この時代から１５０年後に生まれる
天才剣士が編み出した構えだ
It's a form that surpasses even Sabi Hakuhei's.
お前たちが知る錆白兵よりも上の使い手だろう
The three-pronged attack that comes from this stance is supposed to be undodgeable.
この形から繰り出される三段突きはかわしようがないって話だぜ
どうすべきだこの場合
What do we do in this situation?
どうすべきも何も
That's obvious.
わたしたちのやるべきことは常に変わらぬ
What we need to do hasn't changed.
交渉はすでに失敗した
Negotiations have already failed.
鑢七花 わが従僕 戦って奪え
Yasuri Shichika, my right hand,
attack and plunder!
委細承知
Order acknowledged!
Kyotou Yasuri.
「虚刀·鑢」 変に加減なんかしねえで全力の斬れ味で来い
Hold nothing back and cut at me with your full strength.
この体で試し斬りをしろ
Test yourself on this body!
It's not even your body!
お前の体じゃねえだろ
But it is my history.
だが 俺の歴史だ
Show me everything you've got.
お前の全てを俺に見せろ
言われなくても見せてやるさ
I was going to anyway.
ただしそのころには あんたは八つ裂きになっているだろうけどな
However, by that point you'll be torn into pieces!
いざ 尋常に
Let the match...
始め
Begin!
What's wrong, Kyotou Yasuri?
どうした 「虚刀·鑢」 完了ってのはそんなもんじゃねえだろ
Surely that's not all a Completed Blade has to offer!
俺を幻滅させるなよ
Don't let me down!
七花
Shichika!
Shichika! Shichika!
七花 七花
Shichika!
七花
What's wrong? Is that the limit of your strength?
どうした お前の力はそんなものか
Shichika!
七花
You're a well-sharpened sword.
研さんされた刀 そんなもんじゃねえよな虚刀流
This isn't your full strength is it, Kyotouryuu?
I see. I understand that future sword style of yours now.
なるほど 未来の剣術ってのがよく分かったよ
これは油断ならないな
I can't let my guard down.
This is my special move.
取って置きだ
Let's see you dodge it!
よけてみせろよ
七花
Shichika!
However...
だけど
It's still no match for Kyotouryuu!
虚刀流の敵じゃない
七花八裂 改
Shichika Hachiretsu...
Kai!
Ryuuryoku
Kakou
Kyouka
Suigetsu
H
i
k
a
R
k
u
y
o
u
Rakka
Rouzeki
Hyakka
Ryouran
Kinjou
Tenka
Kachou
Fuugetsu
I-I see.
なっ なるほど 悪くない
Not bad at all.
Hey, I don't really get it but,
なあ 俺にはよく分からないんだけど
あれってホントに四季崎記紀だったのか
was that really Shikizaki Kiki?
I wonder.
さあな
やはり真庭鳳凰がただ乱心しただけなのかもしれぬ
It may just have been Maniwa Houou gone insane.
じゃあ これで真庭の生き残りは
Then the only remaining Maniwa is that Pengin guy?
あいつ 人鳥だけってことになるのか
Pengin, huh?
人鳥か 生かされておればよいがな
It'd be nice if he were still alive.
わたしたちにはどうすることもできぬことだ
It's nothing we can change.
The reality is, the Shogunate has branded the Maniwa Corps as traitors.
真庭忍軍は 幕府にとって裏切り者であることは確かだ
実際にどういうつもりで動いていたとしても
No matter what their intentions might have actually been,
右衛門左衛門が 内部監察官として動いたと主張すれば
if Emonzaemon acts on the authority of Internal Affairs, I can't oppose him.
わたしには言葉がないのだ
You almost sound as though you'd rather Pengin weren't killed.
まるで人鳥が殺されることを望んでないみたいな言いようだな
同情の余地がないのはずっと言っておるとおりだがな
Though, I've always said there's no room for sympathy.
It's nothing I'd have said to Shikizaki Kiki, but when I saw the carnage in that village,
四季崎記紀の物言いではないが
あの里の惨状を見てしまうと
わたしでも思うところがないわけでもない
it's not like I didn't feel for them.
Not just the Maniwa Corps, either.
真庭忍軍に限らぬ
In this past year, we've traveled all over Japan.
この一年 そなたと日本中を旅した
そして いろんな土地といろんな人間を見た
And we've seen various people in various places.
I've come to realize how narrow-sighted I was.
いかに自分の見識が狭いものだったか思い知らされたよ
わたしは 何も知らなかったのだ
I really didn't know anything.
That's not like you.
あんたらしくもねえ
After we descend from here, we'll soon be in Owari.
ここを下れば すぐに尾張か
We managed to make it before sundown.
どうにか日が落ちる前に間に合ったな
Yeah.
Let's hurry, then.
では 急ぐとしよう
What are you doing, idiot?
何をしておるか このたわけが
You're my trusted partner now, right?
そなたは わたしの腹心になると言ったであろう
Yeah, but...
言ったけど
Trusted partners are supposed to hold their master's hand when they walk!
腹心は歩くときは あるじと手をつなぐものだ
Really?
そうなのか
Yeah!
そうなのだ
I thought you weren't supposed to say that until the very end, in order to keep me alert and on the ready.
俺から 緊張感と集中力を失わせないために
そういうことは 思っても最後まで言わないもんだと思ってたぜ
You've also changed quite a bit during this journey this past year.
そなたもこの一年の旅路の中で ずいぶんと変わったであろう
You've come to know of society and the world,
世間を知り 世界を知り
and you've gained knowledge and resolve.
知識を得 覚悟を得
You really have grown.
そなたは成長した
そなたほどではなくともな
And while it may not be to the same extent as you, I've also changed during this year-long journey.
わたしだって 一年も旅をすれば変わるさ
Not only that, I've also experienced many things for the first time on this journey.
それだけこの旅路はわたしにとっても 初体験のことが多かった
Stop grinning like that, it's weird!
にやにやするな 気持ち悪い
You're grinning too, you know.
お前だってにやついてたじゃないか
I am not!
にやついてなどおらぬわ
さすがにお姫さまは目ざといな
The Princess is as sharp as ever.
わたしたちの行動を見越して 早速先手を打ってきたか
She predicted when we'd arrive here and made her move first.
Well, that's fine.
まあよい 話が早くて助かるといえよう
It saves us time, since we can cut to the chase.
If she made the first move, we just have to return it with our own.
先手を打たれたならば 後手を返せばよいだけだ
Shichika, the political war begins now.
七花 政略戦を始めるぞ
俺には何もできねえけどな
I can't really help you out then.
そばで 安らぎをくれれば それでよい
Standing steady by my side is enough.
そっか
I see.
Yo, Emonzaemon-dono.
よお 右衛門左衛門殿
I suppose I should thank you for coming to meet us?
出迎えご苦労といったところかな
ご覧のとおり「毒刀·鍍」の収集には成功した
As you can see, we've successfully procured Dokutou Mekki.
Shouldn't you have something to say to me at this point in time?
事がここに至ってしまえば
そなたは私に言っておかねばならぬことがあるのではないか
I guess you're right.
ああ そうだな
いつかの姫さまではないが
I'm not the Princess from back then, but allow me to congratulate you.
おめでとうと言わせてもらおう
これであなたは野望へまた一歩 歩み寄ったわけだからな
You've managed to take one more step towards fulfilling your ambitions.
Ambitions?
野望 そんなものを抱いた覚えはないが
I don't recall ever having any.
Really?
そうか ならば復讐と言った方がいいか
Then maybe I should call it revenge?
Daughter of the former Lord of Oushuu, Hida Takahito,
かつての奥州の顔役 飛騨鷹比等の一人娘
Princess Yousha.
TL Note: Yousha - Permit
容赦姫さま
Forgive me!
あしからず
と とがめ
T-Togame?
Now then, Strategian.
さて 奇策士よ
あなたは何と言って死ぬのかな
What will be your dying words?
Right now, at this instant,
今 この瞬間
the final Deviant Blade that Shikizaki Kiki forged,
四季崎記紀が鍛えし変体刀
最後の１本
Kyoutou Yasuri, is now Perfected.
「虚刀·鑢」が完成 いえ 完了したのでございます
Nay, Completed.
The story of Katanagatari on this month and this evening ends here.
『刀語』 今月こよいのお楽しみはこれまでにございます
次回 完結
To be concluded next time.
karada ga kokoro wo shinjite
My body trusts in my heart
okizari ni sareta nara
If I'm abandoned
kuzureru koto wo shiritsutsu
I will continue to feel ruin
nasake wo kakeru
I show pity
yomigaeru tagai no yabou
Our revived hopes
dochira ka ga horobiru made wa
Until one of us perishes
体が心を信じて　置き去りにされたまま
nazorae tagai wo idaku
Will be embraced
samayoeru bourei tachi yo
Departed spirits adrift
buji nara oshiete yo
If you are safe, tell me
崩れのことを雫　情けをかける
todokanai koe ga hibiita
My unreaching voice resounded
munashisa wo yadosu aiiro no
Sleep to the emptiness
uragiri no kotoba ni nemure
Clinging to words of indigo betrayal
karada ga kokoro wo shinjite
My body trusts in my heart
蘇る互いの野望　どちらが滅びるまでは
tatakai wo kakenuketa
I overtook the fight
kanashii uso de kurushimu you na
Like suffering from sad lies
名と変えた互いを抱く　彷徨える亡霊達よ
yowaki na kakugo wa yurusanai
I won't forgive such cowardly determination
misekake no tadashisa ga
The hidden truth
理不尽なら教えてよ　届かない恋が響いた
misekake no yasashisa e to
Towards the hidden kindness
kuzureru  koto wo shiritsutsu
Continues to feel ruin
空しさを宿す愛よりも　裏切りの言葉に眠れ
nasake wo kake you
Let's show pity
nasake wo
Pity...
体が心を信じて　戦いを駆け抜けた
The successor must be human.
That means you are the successor.
過信不足で　苦しむような弱気な覚悟は許さない
All your history was a lie.
Your history was certainly not a lie.
見せ掛けの正しさが
Was the truth really true?
Or was it absolute?
見せ掛けの優しさへと
That was all just a fantasy.
崩れることを雫
I never believed in anyone from the start.
I just... wanted to meet you.
情けをかけよう　情けを
Next time, Katanagatari's final episode:
Etou
Jyuu
Gun,
the Flame
Etou Jyuu